Esther Rolf

■ esther.rolf@colorado.edu | ★ www.estherrolf.com | 🖸 estherrolf

Research

I study statistical and geospatial machine learning. My research blends methodological and applied techniques to design and analyze machine learning algorithms and systems with an emphasis on usability, data-efficiency and fairness. My current research directions include developing algorithms and infrastructure for reliable environmental monitoring using machine learning, and understanding the multifaceted nature of representation in data and how that affects our ability to train fair and effective machine learning systems.

Academic Positions

Harvard University Cambridge MA, USA

POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW 2022 — present

Joint fellowships from the Center for Research on Computation and Society & the Harvard Data Science Initiative

University of Colorado Boulder Boulder, Colorado

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR
VISITING PROFESSOR
2022 — 2024

Education

University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA

Ph.D., Computer Science, advised by Michael I. Jordan and Benjamin Recht

2016 - 2022

• Thesis: Incorporating Intent, Impact, and Context for Beneficial Machine Learning

Princeton University Princeton NJ, US

B.S.E. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

2012 - 2016

- Graduated summa cum laude. Department GPA: 4.0, Overall GPA: 3.83
- Senior Thesis: Information Complexity Analysis of Topological Communication Bounds, advised by Mark Braverman
- Junior Thesis: Probabilistic Prediction of Metadata for Sparse Datasets, advised by Elad Hazan

Awards and Fellowships _

2023	SDG Digital Gamechangers award UNDP and ITU	Ney York, NY
2021	Rising Star in AI for Social Good Harvard Center for Research on Computation and Society	Cambridge, MA
2020	Google PhD Fellowship	Berkeley, CA
2019	Best Paper Award NeurIPS Joint Workshop on AI for Social Good	Vancouver, Canada
2019	Global Policy Lab Doctoral Fellow	Berkeley, CA
2018	Best Paper Award International Conference of Machine Learning (ICML)	Stockholm, Sweden
2016	National Science Foundation (NSF) Graduate Fellowship	Berkeley, CA
2016	Berkeley Stonebraker Fellowship	Berkeley, CA
2016	Princeton University Student Teaching Award	Princeton, NJ
2016	CRA Outstanding Undergraduate Researcher Honorable Mention	Princeton, NJ

Research Internships _____

Research Intern Virtual

GOOGLE RESEARCH

November 2021- January 2022

Hosted by Ben Packer, Alex Beutel, and Fernando Diaz.

Research Intern Redmond, WA (virtual)

MICROSOFT RESEARCH

May - July 2021

Hosted by Nebojsa Jojic.

Publications

Conference Papers

OCTOBER 12, 2023 ESTHER ROLF · CV 1

- Fairness and representation in satellite-based poverty maps: Evidence of urban-rural disparities and their impacts on downstream policy (w/ Emily Aiken and Joshua Blumenstock).
 - $Emily Aiken, \textbf{Esther Rolf*}, Joshua \ Blumenstock. \ \textit{International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI)}. \ 2023.$
- Resolving label uncertainty with implicit posterior models.
 Esther Rolf*, Nikolay Malkin*, Alexandros Graikos, Ana Jojic, Caleb Robinson, Nebojsa Jojic. Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI). 2022. Oral Presentation.
- Representation matters: assessing the importance of subgroup allocations in training data.

 Esther Rolf, Theodora Worledge, Benjamin Recht, Michael I. Jordan. *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. 2021.
- Balancing competing objectives with noisy data: score-based classifiers for welfare-aware machine learning. Esther Rolf, Max Simchowitz, Lydia T. Liu, Sarah Dean, Daniel Björkegren, Moritz Hardt, Joshua Blumenstock. *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*. 2020.
- Post-estimation smoothing: a simple baseline for learning with side information.

 Esther Rolf, Michael I. Jordan, Benjamin Recht. International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS). 2020.
- Delayed impact of fair machine learning.

 Lydia T. Liu, Sarah Dean, Esther Rolf, Max Simchowitz, Moritz Hardt. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML). 2018. Best Paper Award.
- Enhancing Wi-Fi signal strength of a dynamic heterogeneous system using a mobile robot provider.

 Esther Rolf, Matt Whitlock, Byung-Cheol Min, Eric T Matson. *Robot Intelligence Technology and Applications (RiTA)*.

 2014.

Journal Papers

- A generalizable and accessible approach to machine learning with global satellite imagery.
 Esther Rolf*, Jonathan Proctor*, Tamma Carleton*, Ian Bolliger*, Vaishaal Shankar*, Miyabi Ishihara, Benjamin Recht, Solomon Hsiang. Nature Communications. 2021.
- A successive-elimination approach to adaptive robotic source seeking.

 Esther Rolf*, David Fridovich-Keil*, Max Simchowitz, Benjamin Recht, Claire Tomlin. *IEEE Transactions on Robotics* (TRO). 2020.
- The effect of large-scale anti-contagion policies on the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic.

 Solomon Hsiang, Daniel Allen, Sebastien Annan-Phan, Kendon Bell, Ian Bolliger, Trinetta Chong, Hannah Druckenmiller, Andrew Hultgren, Luna Yue Huang, Emma Krasovich, Peiley Lau, Jaecheol Lee, Esther Rolf, Jeanette Tseng, Tiffany Wu. Nature. 2020.

Workshop Papers

- Evaluation Challenges for Geospatial ML.
 Esther Rolf. Workshop on Machine Learning for Remote Sensing (ICLR). 2023.
- Striving for data-model efficiency: Identifying data externalities on group performance.

 Esther Rolf, Ben Packer, Alex Beutel, Fernando Diaz. Workshop on Trustworthy and Socially Responsible Machine Learning, Neural Information Processing Symposium (NeurIPS). 2022.
- Can Strategic Data Collection Improve the Performance of Poverty Prediction Models?.

 Satej Soman, Emily Aiken, Esther Rolf, Joshua Blumenstock. Artificial Intelligence for Humanitarian Assistance and Disaster Response Workshop (NeurIPS). 2021.
- Balancing competing objectives for welfare-aware machine learning with imperfect data.
 Esther Rolf, Max Simchowitz, Lydia T. Liu, Sarah Dean, Daniel Björkegren, Moritz Hardt, Joshua Blumenstock. Joint Workshop on Al for Social Good Workshop, Neural Information Processing Symposium (NeurIPS). 2019. Best Paper Award.
- Ground control to Major Tom: the importance of field surveys in remotely sensed data analysis.

 Ian Bolliger, Tamma Carleton, Solomon Hsiang, Jonathan Kadish, Jonathon Proctor, Benjamin Recht, Esther Rolf, Vaishaal Shankar. Data for Good Exchange. 2017.

Talks

Toward data focused machine learning: Efficiency, responsibility, and beyond

Google Research Seminar July 2023

^{*} denotes equal contribution

Microsoft New England Machine Learning Ideas Seminar	October 2022		
A generalizable and accessible approach to machine learning with global satellite imagery			
Summer at Census (virtual) Workshop	July 2022		
United States Census Bureau	Nov. 2021		
Berkeley School of Information Data Science Immersion Experience	Nov. 2021		
Harvard Center for Research on Computation and Society Rising Star Speaker Series	Apr. 2021		
CGIAR Big Data in Agriculture: Digital Dynamism for Adaptive Food Systems	Oct. 2020		
American Geophysical Union	Dec. 2019		
ImageXD Conference at Berkeley Institute of Data Science	Sep. 2019		
Balancing competing objectives for welfare-aware ML with imperfect data			
NeurIPS Joint Workshop on AI for Social Good	Dec. 2019		
Delayed impact of fair machine learning			
Sigmetrics Conference	June 2019		

Teaching

Guest Lectures

HARVARD CS 96: SYSTEM DESIGN PROJECTS: MACHINE LEARNING FOR SOCIAL IMPACT

Spring 2023

• Data and ML: Historical, academic, and practical perspectives.

Graduate Student Instructor

UC BERKELEY DS 102, DATA, INFERENCE, AND DECISIONS

Fall 2019

- Developed curriculum and materials for the inaugural semester of the capstone data science course at UC Berkeley.
- Taught weekly discussion sections and code-based lab sections.

UC BERKELEY CS 189/289A. INTRODUCTION TO MACHINE LEARNING

Fall 2018

- Developed and tailored course materials and exams at mixed undergraduate/graduate level machine learning.
- Taught weekly sections, prepared and delivered exam review sessions.

Undergraduate TA and Grader

PRINCETON CS 340: REASONING ABOUT COMPUTATION

Fall 2015-Spring 2016

Held Lab TA office hours with a mix of lecture-style review content and one-on-one problem-based discussions. Graded.

PRINCETON CS 126, 226: INTRO TO PROGRAMMING, ALGORITHMS AND DATA STRUCTURES

Fall 2013-Spring 2015

• Graded undergraduate programming assignments and exams. Both courses are taught in java.

Workshop and Seminar Organization _____

Good Data Seminar UC Berkeley

ORGANIZER September 2018 - Spring 2020

In 2018 I initiated this cross-disciplinary seminar spanning members from Computer Science, Public Policy and the Information School, with regular guests from Statistics and Economics. For several years I organized the weekly meetings during which graduate students and postdocs presented research in progress, workshopped new ideas, and gave tutorials on fundamentals cross-cutting these fields.

Workshop Organization

CO-ORGANIZER

- Harvard CRCS Workshop on Al-Assisted Decision-Making for Conservation: 2022
- NeurIPS Workshop on Artificial Intelligence for Humanitarian Assistance and Disaster Response Workshop: 2021

Reviewing_

Conference Reviewing

- ACM Conference on Equity and Access in Algorithms, Mechanisms, and Optimization (EAAMO): 2023
- International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS): 2022
- Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS): 2019 (Among the top 400 reviewers)
- International Conference of Machine Learning (ICML): 2019

Journal Reviewing

- Environmental Data Science: 2023
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters: 2021

Workshop Reviewing

- NeurlPS Workshop on AI + Humanitarian Assistance and Disaster Relief: 2021
- NeurIPS Workshop on Consequential Decision Making in Dynamic Environments: 2020

Service_

AGU Position Statement Panel: Data

San Francisco, CF

Fall 2023

Panel Member

• Served on panel to update the Data position statement of the American Geophysical Union.

CalMentorsBerkeley, CA

Tutor Fall 2020

• Met weekly to virtually tutor students from around the bay area who may be disproportionately affected by the challenges of online learning. Provide support for students to complete homework assignments and reinforce concepts from class in math subjects ranging from geometry to calculus.

Women in Computer Science and Engineering

Berkeley, CA

SOCIAL CHAIR

Fall 2018 - Spring 2019

• Planned events fostering community among female graduate students and the wider community of computer science and electrical engineering. Mentored new female graduate students.

Mentoring

Students Mentored (Individual Research)

• Theodora Worledge, UC Berkeley, Undergraduate.

Berkeley Al Research (BAIR) Undergraduate Mentoring Program

2017, 2019

• Mentored undergraduate students from underrepresented groups who are considering a career in research.